<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dominick Ng</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://dominickng.com/feeds/misc.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://dominickng.com/</id><updated>2014-05-13T00:00:00+10:00</updated><entry><title>Migrations</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2014/05/migrations/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-05-13T00:00:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2014-05-13:blog/2014/05/migrations/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I have been compelled by guilt into addressing this long silence (with my last
entry coming nearly 8 months ago!). It has been an extraordinarily busy time,
and I'm hopefully nearing the end of a PhD and my studenthood. Excitement lies
just over the horizon! And so here is a brand spanking new website and blog
design, as well as a migration away from Blogger and onto a statically
generated site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the near future I'll write a full guide on how to migrate from Blogger to
a &lt;a href="http://getpelican.com"&gt;Pelican-powered&lt;/a&gt; static site backed by
&lt;a href="https://pages.github.com"&gt;Github Pages&lt;/a&gt; and hosted on a custom
domain. There's a few tricks along the way - including perhaps the most
important one of properly redirecting the Blogger site and posts to the new
site. Google makes it quite difficult to easily migrate away from Blogger -
particularly if you don't move to an option with your own hosting but use
Github Pages instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There will also be further US travel tales, new Europe travel tales, and maybe
even some PhD related material too. It's a brave new world here in 2014.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Tech"></category></entry><entry><title>Closing the doors on the lucky country</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2013/07/closing-doors-on-lucky-country/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-07-21T00:00:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2013-07-21:blog/2013/07/closing-doors-on-lucky-country/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I am a first-generation Australian. My parents arrived in this country nearly forty years ago, seeking better opportunities for the future. I was born in a small country town in regional New South Wales, and I had the great fortune to grow up in a safe, welcoming environment, free from many of the anxieties and insecurities that plague much of the Western World as well as the terrifying dangers and tensions rife in many developing countries. I am very lucky to be where I am today, and much of that has come from where and when I was born. My parents have worked tirelessly each and every single day since they arrived to create the best possible environment for me and my younger brother and sister. They started from nothing and with nothing.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have had the privilege of attending prestigious universities, living in one of the world's most naturally beautiful cities, and meeting and working with incredible people from all around the world. Australia is a highly advanced, politically stable, secure, prosperous, and blessed country - and we are far luckier for it than billions around the world. I love living here, and after a year spent in the United States and countless travels across Asia and Europe, I can't imagine wanting to settle any where else.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2013/byboatnovisa.jpg"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Image from &lt;http://www.immi.gov.au/visas/humanitarian/novisa/&gt; \- 21st July 2013&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It's taken me a few days to figure out exactly what chills me about the Australian Government's &lt;a href="http://www.immi.gov.au/visas/humanitarian/novisa/"&gt;new immigration policy&lt;/a&gt;, where asylum seekers arriving on boats without visas will be unilaterally barred from our shores. It's deeper than dismay at the lurch to the right, the disgustingly insular rhetoric printed in the media, or the scathingly predictable three-word slogans emanating from the politicians. I felt that something else, something more important was wrong. And what it boils down to is this.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Will people like me be welcome in Australia in the years to come?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are a country of immigrants. Every single one of us, European, American, Asian, African, Middle-Eastern, Latino or Pacific Islander. In fact, I'd wager that a huge proportion of the population has some ancestor who arrived here on a boat and probably without a visa. Yet, year by year, we seem to be growing increasingly hostile to those who've come across the sea to share in our boundless plains. Now, I have experienced racism; seen the ugly scrawls of GO HOME on the windows of my parent's shop and endured the judgmental banalities of the misinformed. I have seen the effects of this on those I care about. I had thought that these were the bad eggs at the fringes of our society - the natural result of growing up as a token minority in an overwhelming Anglo-Saxon community. The vast majority of the people I know share my views. But the immigration policies of our two mainstream political parties suggests that I must have a very narrow circle indeed.   &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, any asylum seeker who comes to Australia by boat without a visa will be forcibly resettled in Papua New Guinea, a country with myriad social, political, and economic troubles. It is more extreme than any immigration policy we have had since the dissolution of the White Australia Policy some 40 years ago. The very notion that one must be pre-approved and issued credentials to seek asylum is laughable considering the circumstances that drive most to seek asylum in the first place. The very notion that it is possible to "stop the boats", to stop people from escaping horrifying situations is laughable. The very notion that the greatest threat to this country is incoming boat arrivals is laughable. But what isn't laughable is what these attitudes say about us as a people, and for that I am deeply ashamed.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Xenophobia is rising across the world, and that is truly saddening. It's pushing governments to undertake ever more draconian measures in the name of satisfying the people. The fear of the different, the exotic, the not-the-same is really what hurts. Countries teeter on the edge of civil and international wars brought on by deep-set prejudices - and in response those countries further embrace those prejudices. It is a circuit that has no end - one that we as a world has pledged time and time again to step away from.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given different circumstances, it could easily be me on one of those boats, floating towards an uncertain tomorrow but away from a catastrophic today. It could be an innumerable number of my friends, most of whom are also recent-generation Australians. Is this what the majority of Australians think of people like us? Is this sense of entitlement - to a country forcibly wrested from its original inhabitants no less - is this the new norm for our society?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We are an embarrassingly fortunate people. And in a world where such fortune is rare, it is our responsibility to do our part to help those without such luck. It is not illegal to seek asylum in Australia. It should be illegal for us to turn away from helping those in need.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Australia"></category><category term="Politics"></category></entry><entry><title>The San Francisco Valentine's Day Pillow Fight</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2013/03/the-san-francisco-valentines-day-pillow/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-03-11T00:00:00+11:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2013-03-11:blog/2013/03/the-san-francisco-valentines-day-pillow/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I don't much like Valentine's Day. But it seems like San Francisco agrees with me, because February 14th in the city features an enormous pillow fight at Justin Herman Plaza, opposite the Ferry Building near Embarcadero. 2013 was the eighth annual incarnation of the event, where hundreds of people gather to hit on strangers with things other than bad pick-up lines.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2013/DSC00241.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fight was due to start at six o'clock sharp, so we left Berkeley clutching our pillows at 5pm (yes, it takes that long to get to San Francisco from Berkeley, even though you can see the city just over the Bay). It was entertaining playing "spot the fellow pillow fighters" on the train; we would exchange sheepish nods in acknowledgement of the shared hilarity of the situation. By the time we passed Oakland and entered the TransBay tunnel, several other people had gotten into the carriage with pillows. We stood out even amongst these because one of our party was in the process of fashioning pillow armour: taping pillows to his arms and legs.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2013/DSC00271.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We made it to the plaza just in time, and were faced with the hilarious sight of hundreds of people milling around with pillows at the ready. Some had come prepared with face masks, scarves, and ski goggles, whilst others had come in costumes. We spotted Captain America and a cow in amongst the crowd.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2013/DSC00247.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Six o'clock came and the pillows began flying. Hundreds of complete strangers, indiscriminately swinging their fluffy weapons of war at each other and laughing all the while. Many people had unwisely brought feather pillows rather than synthetic ones; the feathered variety would burst quickly and spray their contents all over people and the plaza. Soon, the tiled ground resembled a winter wonderland, and the air was full of white. It was hard to avoid swallowing the flying fluff; I think I was still coughing up feathers later that evening, and picking them out of my shoes and clothes.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2013/DSC00273.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sun set and the night lights came on. The field of war lapsed into darkness, and the attacks became even more random. People waded through the crowd, swinging their pillows at anyone or anything in their path. Surprisingly enough, some of the roughest participants were tiny little children, dressed in caps and hoods, screaming at the tops of their lungs as they sprinted through legs, thwacking at will. Some people with evident anger management issues were in the crowd; some strikes were definitely more venomous than others. But the vast majority of people were taking the event in the right spirit: swinging with some force, but always with a smile on their face.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2013/DSC00275.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Purportedly, the event cost the San Francisco Department of Public Works $5000 to &lt;a href="http://www.nbcbayarea.com/news/weird/Great-San-Francisco-Pillow-Fight-Tab-Is-5K-191485561.html"&gt;clean up&lt;/a&gt; (an affair that mostly involves hoovering up feathers and picking up discarded pillow carcasses). Thankfully, they don't seem too miffed at the deliberate mess, saying that the event is becoming a regular part of the San Francisco Valentine's Day experience. I can certainly say that it's the strangest, yet most entertaining experience I've had on February 14th. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Valentine's Day"></category><category term="San Francisco"></category><category term="USA"></category></entry><entry><title>Price gouging?</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2012/12/price-gouging/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-12-29T00:00:00+11:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-12-29:blog/2012/12/price-gouging/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There is a lot of talk about how Australians are overcharged for hardware and software items compared to other countries. The Federal Parliament has convened a Standing Committee on Infrastructure and Communications to investigate "price gouging" in the IT industry, particularly from the likes of Apple, Adobe, Microsoft, and other tech giants.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States is a particularly common source of ire, and many people point at US prices compared to Australia as evidence for gouging. There's a number of reasons why a straight price comparison with the US can be misleading:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Australia has a fixed 10% sales tax applied to the vast majority of goods and services. This tax is included in the advertised price, meaning that the true price of something is actually about 91% of the price on the sticker.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The US has a variable rate of &lt;em&gt;state general sales tax&lt;/em&gt; that differs depending on your location. Some states, such as Alaska and Oregon, have &lt;em&gt;no&lt;/em&gt; general sales tax. California has one of the highest total tax rates in the US, at 9.75%; very few states have more than 10% tax in total.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Most importantly, &lt;em&gt;almost all advertised US prices in stores and online do not include tax&lt;/em&gt;. The tax is added at the checkout or when finalising an online purchase. So when you see a camera priced at $600 in a US store, its true price will actually be somewhere in the region of $600 - $660, depending on the amount of tax applicable.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Australia is a much smaller market than the United States, meaning that it's harder to achieve economies of scale in shipping and selling to an Australian audience. This means smaller price savings can be passed onto consumers due to sheer volume of sales.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, if you check out the &lt;a href="http://store.apple.com/us"&gt;US Apple Store&lt;/a&gt;, and add approximately 10% to the price of everything, you get nearly identical prices to the &lt;a href="http://store.apple.com/us"&gt;Australian Apple Store&lt;/a&gt;. Now, there may be an argument to say that the prices should be exactly identical, but maybe the Australian market is simply more expensive to service than the US on a per item basis.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This isn't to say that there isn't price gouging going on. Adobe's Creative Suite 6 Master Collection costs &lt;a href="http://www.adobe.com/products/creativesuite/mastercollection.html"&gt;$2,599 in the US&lt;/a&gt;, but&lt;a href="http://www.adobe.com/au/products/creativesuite/mastercollection.html"&gt; $4,344 in Australia&lt;/a&gt;! Subscription prices for the software are also 25% more expensive in Australia - $49.99 per month in the US against $62.99 per month in Australia. There's definitely something fishy going on here: software can be delivered for the same cost over the internet anywhere in the world, and tax differences don't account for such huge discrepancies.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Australians are certainly being overcharged for some things. But it pays to remember sometimes that prices are simply advertised differently in different countries.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;script type= "text/javascript"&gt;
    if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
        var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
        mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
        mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
        mathjaxscript.src = 'https:' == document.location.protocol
                ? 'https://c328740.ssl.cf1.rackcdn.com/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML'
                : 'http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
        mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
            "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
            "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
            "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
            "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
            "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
            "    displayAlign: 'center'," +
            "    displayIndent: '0em'," +
            "    showMathMenu: true," +
            "    tex2jax: { " +
            "        inlineMath: [ ['$','$'] ], " +
            "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
            "        processEscapes: true," +
            "        preview: 'TeX'," +
            "    }, " +
            "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
            "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'black ! important'} }" +
            "    } " +
            "}); ";
        (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
    }
&lt;/script&gt;
</summary><category term="USA"></category><category term="Australia"></category><category term="Currency"></category></entry><entry><title>Four hour workweeks and outsourcing</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2012/10/i-went-to-talk-by-self-styled-lifestyle/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-30T00:00:00+11:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-10-30:blog/2012/10/i-went-to-talk-by-self-styled-lifestyle/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I went to a talk by a self-styled "lifestyle entrepreneur" today. These people describe themselves as people who work in fields that fit with their lifestyle and preferences, be it to travel around the world, achieve moral or ethical goals, or find self actualisation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One story he told really struck me the wrong way. He was describing how he was being introduced to the marvels of Chinese factory production in the mid-2000s, and how, having just read "The Four Hour Workweek" by Timothy Ferriss, decided to try and combine the two concepts into a business idea.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To me, that just sounded like he was trying to drastically reducing his own working hours by outsourcing (and multiplying!) them to other people who would work for less and produce more.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm not saying I have anything in particular against lifestyle entrepreneurs in general. And I recognise that there are economic arguments and the like involved too. But something about the story just seemed... wrong. It may have been the slightly cavalier way that he told it, or how it seemed to just trivialise people's lives, just because of the differing work expectations. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Outsourcing"></category></entry><entry><title>Hugs</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2012/10/hugs/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-10-28T00:00:00+11:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-10-28:blog/2012/10/hugs/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;There are times when all you need is a hug.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/bearhug.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hug someone today. You don't know how much they might need it. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term=""></category></entry><entry><title>Things that people don't realise about Australia (I)</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2012/09/things-that-people-dont-realise-about/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-09-02T00:00:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-09-02:blog/2012/09/things-that-people-dont-realise-about/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As I meet people from all over America and the world, it's fun addressing some common misconceptions about my homeland. I thought that I'd jot down a few of my favourites so far, and add to the list as it grows.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1. Australia has 22.5 million people, but roughly the same landmass as continental USA. We're the sixth largest country by landmass in the world, but we have less than 4 people per square kilometre (that's a square with sides of roughly 1100 yards for the imperial folk).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/aust-usa-map.jpg"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Image from &lt;a href="http://petergrantfineart.wordpress.com/2010/06/21/the-size-of-australia-vs-usa/"&gt;http://petergrantfineart.wordpress.com/2010/06/21/the-size-of-australia-vs-usa/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Despite stereotypes, over 80% of Australians live within 100km of the coast, and the country is one of the most urbanised in the world. This is mostly due to the fact that vast tracts of the country are borderline uninhabitable.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3. We harvest, consume, and export one of our national animals, the kangaroo.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4. Hardly anyone (at least, in my experience) uses the phrase "&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Shrimp_on_the_barbie"&gt;shrimp on the barbie&lt;/a&gt;".  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5. The capital is Canberra, a city created because Sydney and Melbourne couldn't agree on which one should be the capital, and compromised with neither.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6. We're possibly the only country that has "misplaced" our national leader. In 1967, Prime Minister Harold Holt went for a swim at the beach and disappeared in heavy surf. The police, army, navy, and air force were all called in for a massive search, but to this day no trace of him as been found. Rumours persist that he was a Chinese spy returning to a submarine off the coast, abducted by a UFO, or running away with a mistress. (In all likelihood, he drowned).  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7. We memoralised Holt by naming a swimming pool after him. You can't make this stuff up. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Australia"></category></entry><entry><title>First steps</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2012/08/first-steps-today-im-re-entering-space/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-08-27T00:00:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-08-27:blog/2012/08/first-steps-today-im-re-entering-space/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I'm re-entering a space that I left some time ago. Many years ago, back in school, we had an assignment to maintain a blog, and post interesting things on it. Unfortunately, the site hosting my blog met the way of a server crash, and that data all disappeared. I've stayed off the blogosphere since then.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've now reached a point where I think it's important to write more stuff down. I don't feel like I'm a forgetful person, but I find myself getting to the end of most days and not remembering all of the interesting things that I did, or conversations I had, or sights I saw. With life full of many meetings, greetings, thoughts, views, and people, everything kind of ends up in a blur.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, by way of introduction: I'm a PhD candidate in computer science at the &lt;a href="http://sydney.edu.au/"&gt;University of Sydney&lt;/a&gt;, Australia. I work in &lt;em&gt;natural language processing&lt;/em&gt;, a subfield of artificial intelligence focused on understanding human languages with computers. Prior to this I completed a Bachelor of Information Technology degree, with Honours majoring in computer science.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/IMG_0187.JPG"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;My desk at UC Berkeley&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the 2012-2013 year I was awarded a &lt;a href="http://fulbright.com.au/"&gt;Fulbright scholarship&lt;/a&gt;, a prestigious award that has given me the opportunity to spend a year at &lt;a href="http://berkeley.edu/"&gt;UC Berkeley&lt;/a&gt; in California. As I type this, I'm about to clock up three weeks in the United States. I think I'm settled in now; it's time to get stuck into things.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm aiming to record some of my experiences as a first-time Statesider, a Fulbright grantee, a computer science grad student in the Bay Area, and an Australian who's a long way from home. I'll muse about things that interest me (and hopefully you, dear reader). Hopefully I'll learn something about myself posting here to. Here goes.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Berkeley"></category></entry></feed>