<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dominick Ng</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://dominickng.com/feeds/reviews.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://dominickng.com/</id><updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+11:00</updated><entry><title>The Hobbit: An Unexpected Journey</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2012/12/the-hobbit-unexpected-journey/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-12-19T00:00:00+11:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-12-19:blog/2012/12/the-hobbit-unexpected-journey/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Peter Jackson's &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; films are one of my favourite cinematic experiences. It's hard to believe that close to a decade has passed since the first one was released. Even now, the trilogy still seems fresh and innovative, its CGI hardly dated amongst many other poorer imitations that have not aged as gracefully. Howard Shore's incredible music remains a heavy part of the rotation through my headphones - and I have seen both the &lt;em&gt;Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; symphony production, and watched the first two films with the fantastic Sydney Symphony Orchestra playing the score live. I'm very much looking forward to seeing &lt;em&gt;The Return of the King&lt;/em&gt; in a similar form next year.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/The-Hobbit-Wallpaper-the-hobbit-33042233-1920-1080.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I've been very much looking forward to Jackson's return to Middle-Earth with &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt;. The road to the film's production has been very rocky, punctuated by studio cash crises, fights over the film rights, and the departure of the original director, Guillermo del Toro. But finally, it seemed like all of the pieces fell into place. Peter Jackson would return to direct, and his writing, production, and effects teams from &lt;em&gt;Rings&lt;/em&gt; returned as well. All of the major cast members signed on again, Howard Shore would write the music, and an amazing Bilbo in Martin Freeman was added. Everything was looking peachy.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, slightly perturbing news started coming forth. &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; would be split into two movies. It would be shot in 3D at double the usual framerate - 48 frames per second, rather than 24 (the human eyes see 60 frames per second; they effect of a higher framerate is to "smooth" the film so it looks more realistic). Early footage was unenthusiastically received, and rather unflatteringly compared to BBC period dramas shot with similar framerates. Then the announcement that additional material from Tolkien's short stories would be incorporated, expanding &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; to &lt;strong&gt;three&lt;/strong&gt; movies - as long as the original trilogy, but from a far smaller source. Like many fans, I was beginning to get slightly worried. Could this team that I had such faith in be led astray by the advancing march of technology?  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I shouldn't have been worried. I saw &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit: An Unexpected Journey&lt;/em&gt; last week, in all of its 3D, high framerate, Dolby Atmos sounding glory, and it was brilliant. Yes, it was definitely too long (at least half an hour could have been cut from the first half), but Jackson has perfected the vision he put forth in &lt;em&gt;Rings&lt;/em&gt;, and produced incredible cinematic art doing it. The acting performances are uniformly  It's not every day you get to the cinema 45 minutes early for a film, and the line is already 150 metres long, snaking upstairs to the next floor.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3D is used excellently in the film. There are many sequences where the camera swoops around the running company, indoors and outdoors, and the immersive 3D effect really makes you feel like you're the camera, flying over the running dwarves, wizard, and hobbit as they flee pursuit. The waterfall at Rivendell is simply spectacular in this format, as are the underground sequences that dominate the second half. The high framerate adds a kind of hyperrealism and clarity to the film, like no other film I've ever seen, and it also distinguishes &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; visually from &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;. It's hard to describe precisely what it looks like... just go see it for yourself. I can see why the look of the film has been divisive, but it is definitely unique.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dolby's Atmos sound technology surrounds the audience completely with speakers. The sound effects genuinely feel like they're coming from all around you - voices fade in and out over your shoulder, the clang of weapons and fighting are enough to make you spin around to see who's there. It was all too much for one person, who left our screening early on complaining that it was just too loud. I thought it was perfect from our position three rows from the very back of the cinema.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; is intended as a less serious work than &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;; the latter pulses with the urgency brought on by the impending triumph of ultimate evil over the entire world, whereas the former focuses on evictees trying to evict their evictor, and the growth in character of an unexpected member of their company. The Dwarven cast of &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; contributes to this; much humour and light-heartedness is wrought from their antics through the film, as was from Gimli in &lt;em&gt;Rings&lt;/em&gt;. But right from the start, the ominous haze that hangs over &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; is missing from &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt;; the placid opening is completely different to the introduction of the Ring that opens the earlier trilogy. (Though the opening of &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; ties in wonderfully with &lt;em&gt;The Fellowship of the Ring&lt;/em&gt;). It's funny - the great advancement in film technology seems at odds with the more lighthearted storyline. It's not a bad thing - just a strange artefact of the prequel coming out a decade after its sequels.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The music reuses many of the themes from &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt;, helping to tie the films together. Hearing each familiar melody was like welcoming back dear old friends. Of the new music, the &lt;em&gt;Misty Mountain&lt;/em&gt; tune (sung by the Dwarven company in the film) is Howard Shore's latest instantly iconic leitmotif. Variations of the theme recur throughout the entire film - perhaps to the point of overexposure. The tune also supplies the melody for Neil Finn's stunning &lt;em&gt;Song of the Lonely Mountain&lt;/em&gt;, which plays over the final credits of the film. Crowded House, Finn's band, is one of my favourite musical groups, and the soundtrack is worth buying for this song alone.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This experience cost $17 - at least one third cheaper than in Australia for the full 3D and high framerate deal. For those still waiting for the film to come out, I highly recommend watching the &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/user/pjacksonwingnutfilms"&gt;video production diaries&lt;/a&gt; on Peter Jackson's YouTube page. You'll get a picture of the love, dedication, and detail that has gone into making this film, and be ever more excited to see it. I have faith that the team will continue this over the next two installments as well.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Overall, while the film was extremely long (close to 3 hours, with a very slow and patient opening...), it was worth every moment. I may wish for tighter editing, but it remains a tour de force in world-building, in immersive cinema, in stories and pictures that take you to another world. I've seen complaints that nothing really happens in the film. This is true to some extent, but &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; makes no pretense at being an action adventure. Rather, it is a beautiful, faithful, and loving adaptation of a classic work of fiction.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a final admission: I've never actually read either &lt;em&gt;The Hobbit&lt;/em&gt; or &lt;em&gt;The Lord of the Rings&lt;/em&gt; (!). I've tried to read both several times since I was in high school, but I've never made it very deep into either. The prose in _The Lord of the Rings _is fairly infamous for being difficult to read, but I've decided that there's no excuse for me to have not read its predecessor (it's already on my &lt;a href="http://blog.dominickng.com/2012/12/kindle-paperwhite.html"&gt;Kindle&lt;/a&gt;!). Stay tuned. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Movies"></category><category term="The Hobbit"></category></entry><entry><title>Kindle Paperwhite</title><link href="http://dominickng.com/blog/2012/12/kindle-paperwhite/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-12-15T00:00:00+11:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-12-15:blog/2012/12/kindle-paperwhite/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I've loved reading for as long as I can remember. Some of my earliest memories are going grocery shopping with my mother every week, and each time getting to buy a new &lt;a href="http://www.randomhouse.com/golden/"&gt;Little Golden Book&lt;/a&gt; - short picture books about nursery rhymes, nature, science, and fairy tales. I built up a huge collection of them, before they were given away to cousins as I grew older.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I grew older I moved into more weighty tomes. Nowadays I own many, many books, and have borrowed many more from friends and libraries. I love the feel of books and the stories they contain within. Yet books are somewhat inconvenient. Tomes such as George R.R. Martin's &lt;em&gt;A Game of Thrones&lt;/em&gt; or Douglas Hofstadter's_ &lt;em&gt;Godel, Escher, Bach&lt;/em&gt;: An Eternal Golden Braid_ are very chunky, and don't lend themselves well to being carted around. Sometimes I'll be reading several things at once, but be restricted in how many of those things I can take with me wherever I go.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Enter an e-reader. A couple of weeks ago, I purchased a Kindle Paperwhite - the newest model in the Amazon line of e-readers. This slim little device has a 6-inch screen, and 2GB of memory that can hold close to a thousand books at a time. It has wireless, so you can connect to your Amazon account and download new books on the fly. You can email your own files (like PDFs) to a special @kindle.com email address, and they'll be forwarded to the device. All this in a package that's actually smaller than most paperback books.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/IMG_0436.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I picked up the official Amazon onyx black leather case for the Kindle as well to give it some extra protection. The case has a beautiful, upmarket feel to it, yet adds little to their Kindle's size. There are magnets in the case which automatically wake the Kindle up when you open the case, and put it to sleep when you close it, saving a press on the tiny on/off button hidden at the bottom of the device. I highly recommend the extra protection, as it really gives me the confidence to treat the Kindle as a go-anywhere device.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Impressively, the Paperwhite also has LED backlighting. Instead of pointing up out of the screen, as with LCD screens, the lights in the Paperwhite are reflected downwards, towards the words on the display. This makes the screen very comfortable to look at - I inevitably find that the LCDs in computers and smartphones tire my eyes out and prompt headaches after prolonged use. I haven't really found a use for a tablet in my life - the combination of a smartphone and a MacBook Air easily handles all of my computing needs - but the Kindle definitely fills a niche and a need.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/IMG_0437.jpg"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Same settings as the picture above, just with the room light off&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The backlight is capable of dialing up to a very high brightness - perfect for reading outdoors in strong sunlight. I haven't yet needed the backlight on, but the screen is very nice even without the backlight - it has a very high resolution for an e-reader, leading to extremely crisp text. Reading on the Kindle is easy, comfortable, and convenient - with most of my library with me at all times, I can read whatever I like, whenever it strikes my fancy. I can search through all of the books, look up word definitions on the fly, and fiddle extensively with the font, margins, and spacings. On top of all that, after two weeks of relatively heavy usage, the battery isn't even below halfway yet. The Kindle is advertised as lasting for up to two months for the average reader, and I definitely believe that.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Paperwhite is solely controlled by a touchscreen. Page turns are a tap of the screen away, with a menu rolling into view with a tap at the top of the screen. Unfortunately, having gotten used to the ultra-response iPhone touchscreen, the e-reader feels glacially slow. Some touches take nearly a second for a response. The e-ink technology also requires an unsightly full refresh every few touches (where the screen essentially wipes itself clean), further slowing response time. Sadly, this is necessary given the current limits of e-ink technology. But, given how long e-ink devices last on a battery charge, and how comfortable they are to read books on, the lack of responsiveness is more than an acceptable compromise.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/IMG_0441.jpg"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Damn ads&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One thing that does aggravate me is that the Kindle displays ads by default, and Amazon charges you $20 for the privilege of removing those ads. While the ads never display when you're actually reading, they occasionally pop up as you're navigating your library, and display permanently as a screensaver when the Kindle is locked and asleep. Thankfully, the screensaver uses no power (hooray e-ink!), but it's still odious to open my Kindle and be greeted by paid advertising. Still, it's not odious enough to convince me to part with an additional $20.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The one feature of a book that I truly miss is ease of navigation. I miss being able to simply &lt;em&gt;open&lt;/em&gt; a book to a random page. Often I'll be looking for a specific passage that I know is in a certain section of the book. The chapter navigation offered in the Kindle is very good, but doesn't quite replicate that ability to flick quickly through a book, peeking at pages every now and again. You also can't skip past five or ten pages at a time - the only available options are jumping to a linked chapter, or turning the page. I'd even settle for a function that jumps to a random page in a specified section of a book. But I guess you can't have everything.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All in all, the Kindle Paperwhite is quickly becoming one of my favourite gadgets. I take it almost everywhere with me, and it has drastically cut down on my dead time - I can simply read for a while if I'm ever caught in a waiting situation. Hats off to Amazon for crafting an excellent e-reader, and my new best friend. &lt;/p&gt;&lt;script type= "text/javascript"&gt;
    if (!document.getElementById('mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#')) {
        var mathjaxscript = document.createElement('script');
        mathjaxscript.id = 'mathjaxscript_pelican_#%@#$@#';
        mathjaxscript.type = 'text/javascript';
        mathjaxscript.src = 'https:' == document.location.protocol
                ? 'https://c328740.ssl.cf1.rackcdn.com/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML'
                : 'http://cdn.mathjax.org/mathjax/latest/MathJax.js?config=TeX-AMS-MML_HTMLorMML';
        mathjaxscript[(window.opera ? "innerHTML" : "text")] =
            "MathJax.Hub.Config({" +
            "    config: ['MMLorHTML.js']," +
            "    TeX: { extensions: ['AMSmath.js','AMSsymbols.js','noErrors.js','noUndefined.js'], equationNumbers: { autoNumber: 'AMS' } }," +
            "    jax: ['input/TeX','input/MathML','output/HTML-CSS']," +
            "    extensions: ['tex2jax.js','mml2jax.js','MathMenu.js','MathZoom.js']," +
            "    displayAlign: 'center'," +
            "    displayIndent: '0em'," +
            "    showMathMenu: true," +
            "    tex2jax: { " +
            "        inlineMath: [ ['$','$'] ], " +
            "        displayMath: [ ['$$','$$'] ]," +
            "        processEscapes: true," +
            "        preview: 'TeX'," +
            "    }, " +
            "    'HTML-CSS': { " +
            "        styles: { '.MathJax_Display, .MathJax .mo, .MathJax .mi, .MathJax .mn': {color: 'black ! important'} }" +
            "    } " +
            "}); ";
        (document.body || document.getElementsByTagName('head')[0]).appendChild(mathjaxscript);
    }
&lt;/script&gt;
</summary><category term="Kindle Paperwhite"></category></entry></feed>