<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>Dominick Ng</title><link href="https://dominickng.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://dominickng.com/feeds/usa.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://dominickng.com/</id><updated>2013-04-24T00:00:00+10:00</updated><entry><title>Terror and the USA</title><link href="https://dominickng.com/blog/2013/04/terror-and-usa/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-04-24T00:00:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2013-04-24:blog/2013/04/terror-and-usa/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;On December 14th, 2012, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sandy_Hook_Elementary_School_shooting"&gt;Adam Lanza went on a rampage&lt;/a&gt; at Sandy Hook Elementary School in Connecticut. Using his mother's own guns, he shot and killed her in their house, and proceeded to murder twenty children and six staff members at the school where she worked. As first responders closed in, he committed suicide by shooting himself through the head. On April 17th 2013, gun control measures to improve criminal background checks, ban assault rifles, and limit the size of magazines was defeated in the US Senate following heavy lobbying by the National Rifle Association.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Late during the Boston Marathon on April 15th, 2013, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Boston_Marathon_bombings"&gt;two explosive devices were detonated&lt;/a&gt; near the finish line of the race. Three people were killed, including an eight year old boy watching his father run in the race, a young restaurant manager, and a Chinese graduate student at Boston University. Hundreds were injured, from superficial cuts to missing limbs. In an unrelated incident, a fire broke out at the John F. Kennedy Presidential Library and Memorial in Boston, causing an evacuation and fears of a simultaneous attack. In the aftermath, amid a massive FBI investigation into the perpetrators, amateur sleuths from Reddit and 4chan &lt;a href="http://www.nydailynews.com/news/national/online-sleuths-boston-manhunt-reddit-4chan-article-1.1322658"&gt;incorrectly accused a 17 year old spectator and a missing Brown university student&lt;/a&gt; of being involved. The teenager has his picture put up all over the internet, and is afraid to leave his house. The family of the missing student, already devastated with worry, were forced to take down Facebook pages pleading for information, and underwent even more unnecessary trauma thanks to the false identifications.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 16th and 17th, 2013, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/2013_ricin_attacks"&gt;letters laced with the deadly poison ricin&lt;/a&gt; were intercepted in Washington DC. One was mailed to a US Senator, and another to the US President Barack Obama. So far, an Elvis impersonator has been detained for mailing the letters, though he was later released without charges amidst evidence that he was being framed.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A fire broke out at the West Fertilizer Company storage and distribution plant near Waco, Texas on April 17th, 2013. As firefighters fought the flames, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/West_Fertilizer_Company_explosion"&gt;a massive explosion erupted&lt;/a&gt; from the facility, levelling hundreds of buildings in the area and sending up a huge mushroom cloud into the air. At least fifteen people have been killed (mostly firefighters called in after the initial fire), and hundreds are injured. The shock wave from the explosion blew out windows for kilometres around, and the force of the disaster registered 2.1 on the Richter scale. While the incident is not regarded as suspicious, its timing immediately following the Marathon bombing was chilling.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Following a holdup at a local 7-Eleven, a campus disturbance was reported at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in Cambridge, just across the river from Boston, late on April 18th, 2013. MIT Police officer Sean Collier was shot, and later died of his wounds in hospital. A massive manhunt was instigated for brothers Tamerlan and Dzhokhar Tsarnaev, believed to have been behind the hold up, the shooting, and the Marathon bombings. It was a night of chaos, with millions around the world following via police radio scanners and social media. Fragmented, conflicting reports of hijackings, gun battles, explosions, and bombs bounced back and forth like lightning. Tamerlan died during the battles in the night, and Boston was practically shut down for a day as police combed the city and its suburbs for his brother. Eventually, Dzhokhar was found heavily injured and hidden in a boat in a backyard. He may face the death penalty for his crimes, and his capture resulted in mass street &lt;a href="http://news.yahoo.com/boston-beyond-thanks-jubilation-080556734.html"&gt;celebrations in the locked-down city&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barely an afterthought was the news of a mass shooting in Seattle, Washington on April 22nd. &lt;a href="http://www.cnn.com/2013/04/22/justice/seattle-shooting/index.html"&gt;A domestic dispute&lt;/a&gt; led to a gunman killing his girlfriend, a neighbour, and two other men before police killed him. The gunman had a valid concealed weapons permit. Such was the week preceding that this news was far overshadowed, and ranked just small headlines on news front pages.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I honestly feel less safe in the US than in Australia. Despite being ensconced behind the greatest arsenal in the history of the world, I find it hard to entirely shake off a sense of insecurity. I'm extra watchful if I'm walking alone at night, or in areas that I do not know well. Not being able to see people's faces or hands on ill-lit streets puts me on edge. I vaguely worry about earthquakes and industrial accidents, even though the likelihood of either is remote.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The issue of guns in the US is particularly upsetting. It may be part of my upbringing in Australia, but I do not believe that the &lt;a href="http://www.npr.org/blogs/thetwo-way/2012/12/21/167785169/live-blog-nra-news-conference"&gt;only thing that can stop a bad guy with a gun is a good guy with a gun&lt;/a&gt;. I want there to be no need for either to have guns in the first place. I want there to be no one sufficiently enraged or desperate to use one. It sickens me that people are capable of murdering twenty children, maiming hundreds, or killing over a domestic dispute. It sickens me that people feel the need to possess high-powered weaponry as a purely defensive measure. The sight of arms or armed guards makes me uneasy, as if their presence suggests a real and present danger. But, while &lt;a href="http://vimeo.com/64432171"&gt;gun control&lt;/a&gt; was an incredible success in Australia, but I fear that our precedent is simply incompatible with the expectations of gun rights in the US. Powerful lobby groups aside, I sadly think that mass shootings simply increase the resolve of many Americans to hold onto their guns. You just cannot win when such a culture pervades the people.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps my impressions of safety in the US are coloured by my arrival experience. Before I had even made it off the airport train in August 2012, someone tried to steal my phone right out of my hand. He did not succeed thanks to the intervention of a complete stranger sitting behind me on the train, who pursued and tackled would-be thief. All of happened as the train pulled into a station in the middle of San Francisco. To this day, I feel tense at that station and in the areas around it, and I'm on guard when I'm riding on the trains. There are streets just blocks away from the city centre that I don't like to walk down.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The United States and Australia are similar in several ways, being relatively young, advanced economies with diverse populations. But the history of the US has been defined by conflict both internal and external: wars to secure the country, its independence, and its ideological identity, and wars to shape the world that we know now. Australia has played but a minor part in these global conflicts, and has not torn itself apart in civil war. In a way, I feel like war is ingrained in the American identity. Its activist (some would call it interfering) streak and superpower status ensures that the United States remains deeply involved in matters of global conflict. Moreover, its history and people demand it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Seeing the events at Boston was surreal for me. I visited the city just two weeks prior to the Marathon bombings, walking around the Public Library and Copley Square where the bombs exploded, and taking pictures of the Stata Building at MIT where Officer Collier - a good guy with a gun - was killed. I stayed with a friend whom I had met in Australia; when the bombs went off she was having lunch in a cafe just a block away from, and is thankfully safe and sound. Boston is a beautiful city, full of life, history, and pride, and I feel very sad at the terror that has struck at it. And this extends to many parts of the United States. The country is breathtakingly, stunningly beautiful, full of incredible landscapes and cityscapes, wild natures and feats of engineering. In my travels so far I have yet to be disappointed at the sights and sounds. It is also the centre of the academic and industrial universes, the place to be on the cutting edge.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some have commented (often flippantly) that destruction and death is par for the course in many countries around the world, and that the outcry for Boston was immeasurably overstated given the final toll. But I do not believe that peace and security in one part of the world can be traded for that in another. Boston is not a war zone, and the city is not the site of brutal civil wars or conflicts. It is not a police state with tight security over its people, curfews in the night hours, and restrictions on what one may do. Its people had the fortune to live in what they thought was a safe place. I am sad for those who have the misfortune to land in the dangerous corners of the world, and for the many who pay for it with their lives every day. I wish that these corners were eradicated, and feel ashamed that they still exist. But I do not dismiss what happened in Boston because of them.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it's unsurprising that insecurity pervades the richest nation in the world. The United States is a complicated place of contradictions, incredibly wealthy and beautiful, but beset by fear, social problems, and economic inequities. It occupies a unique place in an envious and sometimes hostile world. While it's easy to preach and scoff, in the end it's truly not easy being American. They bear a heavy burden, and pay for it every single day. I'm not sure if I would want to carry that load as well for the rest of my life. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Terrorism"></category><category term="USA"></category></entry><entry><title>NBA Basketball</title><link href="https://dominickng.com/blog/2012/12/nba-basketball/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-12-03T00:00:00+11:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-12-03:blog/2012/12/nba-basketball/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;America is a country of sports fans. The three biggest sports are gridiron football, basketball, and baseball. Having experienced the insanity of college football, I set my eyes on the NBA, attending the December 1st game between the Golden State Warriors and Indiana Pacers at Oracle Arena in Oakland. For those unfamiliar with the nomenclature, California is sometimes called "the Golden State", and the Warriors are the local Bay Area team.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/IMG_0427.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;NBA teams play several times a week, adding up to 82 games a season - before adding in playoffs! This is in sharp contrast to the more bruising gridiron, where the season ticks by one game per week and less than 20 per year. However, all pro sports in America share a "conference" system, where the teams are divided into regions that compete for playoff spots, before advancing to knock-out games between the ultimate winners of each region. With over 30 teams, this seems an appropriately fair way to run things.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The level of support for sport in America is astounding. The vast majority of the 20,000 seat arena was filled for the game, with raucous music, shouting, ice-cream and drink sellers in amongst people jostling to get to their seats. I thought Australians loved sport. But Americans love watching sport, and they love watching it live.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Golden State Warriors actually have an Australian player - centre Andrew Bogut, recently traded from Milwaukee. Unfortunately, Bogut is currently injured, and did not participate in the game. Warriors fans seem to think that he's a great player - he just need to recuperate and get back on the court.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The game itself was an entertaining affair - I could appreciate the skill of the players as the dribbled, stepped, spun, and shot their way through. I still don't understand the foul system at all (as best I can tell, it's just totally arbitrary), but basketball moves &lt;em&gt;fast&lt;/em&gt;, and keeps moving. In the end, the Warriors edged out the Pacers 103-93, built primarily on a burst of accurate scoring right after half time. The double digit buffer from this was never lost, greatly pleasing the home crowd.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/IMG_0432.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike football, basketball moves forward with relatively minimal interruptions. Advertising at basketball is typically of the more subtle background billboard variety, as opposed to the in-your-face televised kind in gridiron. The breaks (due to timeouts or quarter breaks) are filled with a crazy variety of entertainment and ritual, including:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;the American national anthem, performed by an acapella group called "The Singing Priests". Members of the Coast Guard were holding the flag during the anthem&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;multiple cheerleader routines at varying levels of clothing skimpiness&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a junior dance group performance (thankfully properly clothed)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;live band and DJ sets, with particularly good (or bad) dancers in the crowd highlighted on the big screens&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a trick-shooting brigade, where shooters in turn sprinted towards the basket and hurled themselves into the air via a trampoline, doing flips and such before dunking the ball. As the spectacle continued, they began passing the ball back to the next person running; the grand finale involved the whole team passing, catching, and flipping before a final dunk&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a boys and girls basketball match during halftime. The boys were much bigger than the girls, and so the girls were unsurprisingly walloped. By the end of their game, the crowd was roaring when the girls had the ball, and practically silent when the boys did&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a t-shirt giveaway, with guys on tricycles riding around the court, and firing t-shirts high into the crowd using modified air guns&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;a pizza giveaway, with free pizzas given to loudly cheering people in the crowd&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, there are some poor chaps at the game whose job it is to wipe away the sweat of players who have fallen to the court. I don't envy them, but I suppose if you're a big basketball fan it's a good way to get an amazing view from courtside.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, the highlight of the game was probably this amazing shot from Jarret Jack. As the clock ticked to zero at the end of the third quarter, Jack found himself with three-quarters of the court between himself and the basket. No problem! He launched the ball and sunk an incredible 3-point shot, clean as a whistle. What a spectacle to see live! &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="text-center"&gt;
  &lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/gTqdLTPmNvI" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="USA"></category><category term="Basketball"></category></entry><entry><title>Obama 2012</title><link href="https://dominickng.com/blog/2012/11/obama-2012/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-11-07T00:00:00+11:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-11-07:blog/2012/11/obama-2012/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I consider it a privilege to have been in California during the 2012 US Presidential Election.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;California is strongly Democratic (as in the political party), and Berkeley is a liberal bastion in the Golden State. Add a strongly left-leaning student body and a convenient time zone, and you have the ingredients for a euphoric night.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/IMG_0368.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The tension began around 5pm, as polls on the East Coast closed and the counting began. Naturally, Romney took an early lead due to the concentration of small, sparsely populated Republican states and counties that counted votes quickly. But Obama's numbers clawed back as the night continued, as swing state after swing state went to Obama. Pennsylvania, Michigan, Wisconsin (the home of the Republican vice-presidential nominee Paul Ryan - Obama even won his home county!), and New Hampshire all went blue. Cheers for each one. Then the West Coast called in - California, Hawaii, Oregon, Washington State. New Mexico. Then Iowa. And finally, Ohio. Obama has won it. The Empire State Building has gone blue. The room erupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We went down to Sproul Plaza on the UC Berkeley campus, where thousands of students and staff had gathered to watch the coverage on an outdoor screen. The atmosphere was electric: chants of "USA! USA! Four more years! Obama!" echoed throughout the night, people ran through the crowd draped in American and rainbow flags to wild cheers, and people danced and sang to "I Gotta Feeling", and "Party in the USA" (possibly the best reaction I've ever seen to a Miley Cyrus number).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fox actually did a live cross to a reporter at the plaza whilst we were waiting for the President's victory speech, resulting in wild screams for the network television audience. The concession speech passed, with momentary boos interjecting amongst Governor Romney's supposedly late-scripted remarks. And finally, after a long, long wait, the victory speech. The appreciation of a grateful President, who had won his final race. The biggest cheer of all as he finished, and acknowledged the crowds that had propelled him to the finish line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/IMG_0372.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I have never experienced anything like it. Call the process archaic. Call it inefficient. Call it whatever you think. Standing there, late at night on the first Tuesday in November, I joined in the cheering, the chanting, the screaming, and the dancing. I felt the shared happiness, the elation that their man had won and won big in a close election. That was democracy in action.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Four more years.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Election 2012"></category><category term="Politics"></category><category term="USA"></category></entry><entry><title>College football</title><link href="https://dominickng.com/blog/2012/09/college-football/" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-09-02T00:00:00+10:00</updated><author><name>Dominick Ng</name></author><id>tag:dominickng.com,2012-09-02:blog/2012/09/college-football/</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Here in Berkeley I'm living in the &lt;a href="http://ihouse.berkeley.edu/"&gt;International House&lt;/a&gt; (affectionately known as I-House). I've previously lived in the International House at Sydney (which we called IH), and sometime soon I'll write more about these places. But earlier today I attended my first college football match, courtesy of some free tickets from I-House. It was the opening game of the season - the California Golden Bears playing at home in Berkeley against Nevada.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I know that college football is a thing here. But I wasn't prepared for just how much of a thing it would be. I-House Berkeley is situated right next to &lt;a href="http://stadium.berkeley.edu/"&gt;California Memorial Stadium&lt;/a&gt;, which has just been rebuilt from the ground up. This was the homecoming match for the stadium and the Bears, who had played in San Francisco last year. As I strolled out of I-House, here was the sight that greeted me:  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/DSC06298.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There were people &lt;em&gt;everywhere&lt;/em&gt;. It seemed like half the population of Berkeley was streaming up the road and into the massive stadium - families, older folk, university students alike. And that was nothing compared to inside...  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure class="image"&gt;
  &lt;img class="img-responsive" src="/images/2012/DSC06309.JPG"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Over 63,000 people turned up to the game. By way of reference, UC Berkeley only has 36,000 students, and the vast majority of people I saw in the streets were just members of the public. As an Australian, having this many people show up to a inter-university sports match is mind-boggling.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The match itself was an error-strewn affair befitting the opening game of the season. The Bears quickly found themselves in a 14-0 hole thanks to some sloppy defence in the first quarter. However, they eventually found some momentum and engineered an exciting comeback to tie the game at 24-24 with 5 minutes left. But critical errors by the Bears in the dying stages of the game allowed Nevada to score a decisive final touchdown to win 31-24 and disappointing the home crowd.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Also somewhat disconcerting to me was just how long American football takes. There's 60 minutes of game time, divided into 4 quarters. But the match took 3 hours 45 minutes to finish! So many things that happen on-field can stop the game clock, and when you throw in a half-time show, timeouts, team strategising, and more, a game really does eat the whole afternoon away. However, the atmosphere was electric, and the crowd was heavily involved throughout. I had a lot of fun, and I'm sure I'll attend more matches this year. Go Bears! &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Berkeley"></category><category term="American Football"></category></entry></feed>